<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A call to a general reformation of manners and manifesting in several particulars the great lets and hinderances thereunto / preached at the arch-deacon of Sudbury's visitation, holden at Kentford in Suffolk in April last, 1700, by Clement Heigham, Esq., now rector of Barrow in Suffolk.</title>
            <author>Heigham, Clement, d. 1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1370A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36595</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15741857</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15741857</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104573</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104573)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1593:63)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A call to a general reformation of manners and manifesting in several particulars the great lets and hinderances thereunto / preached at the arch-deacon of Sudbury's visitation, holden at Kentford in Suffolk in April last, 1700, by Clement Heigham, Esq., now rector of Barrow in Suffolk.</title>
                  <author>Heigham, Clement, d. 1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Darby for Richard Thurlbourn ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew V, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104573:1"/>
            <p>A CALL To a General Reformation of Manners. AND Manifeſting, in ſeveral Particulars, the great Lets and Hinderances thereunto. Preached at the Arch-Deacon of <hi>Sudbury</hi>'s Viſitation, holden at <hi>Kentford</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> in <hi>April</hi> laſt, 1700.</p>
            <p>By <hi>CLEMENT HEIGHAM,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> now Rector of <hi>Barrow</hi> in <hi>Suffolk.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. XXVIII. 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They that forſake the Law, praiſe the Wicked; but ſuch as keep the Law, contend with them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Darby</hi> for <hi>Richard Thurlbourn</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller in <hi>Cambridg,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104573:2"/>
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:104573:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, and truly Noble, CHARLES Lord Viſcount <hi>Townſhend.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Much Honoured and Noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HIS Majeſty's Proclamation againſt Immoralities, and the Honourable Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment piouſly concurring, by ſome good Laws, to aſſiſt and ſtrengthen the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:104573:3"/>in the ſuppreſſing of Vice; as it gave me a ſecret Pleaſure, ſo it did encourage me to frame and preach this following Diſcourſe, and for expoſing this Sermon in print to a more publick View. I am not without hopes it may do ſome good upon ſuch as ſhall caſt their Eye upon it (the Diſcourſe being on an Argument wherein all good Men do agree) but more eſpecially it may let ſome that are in great Authority ſee that there are great Lets and Hinderances amongst us as to an univerſal Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and ſome of them are ſuch Lets and Hinderances, as only the Wiſdom of the Nation in Parliament can remove.</p>
            <p>And I am the more emboldned to make uſe of Your Lordſhip's Name, and
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:104573:3"/>to crave Your Patronage, not only upon the account of Your great Honour, emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Parts, and moſt agreeable Virtue (whereby You ſhine amongſt our Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and do attract the Affections of all Good Men) but becauſe great Examples are powerful, and have a mighty Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to bear down Vice, and to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Goodneſs, And I am fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded Your Lordſhip will in Your High Place endeavour to promote that Great Deſign which this Diſcourſe points at, which is, to promote the true and laſting Happineſs of our Church and State; and which can be effected by no other means than by making the Almighty God our Patron and Friend, which can only be by depreſſing Wickedneſs, and encourag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Piety and univerſal Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="vi" facs="tcp:104573:4"/>And upon theſe accounts it is that I pray for Your Lordſhip's Health and Happineſs in this Life, and Your end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Glory hereafter; and ſhall always approve my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt honouring, moſt Faithful, and moſt Obedient Kinſman, and Humble Servant, <hi>CLEMENT HEIGHAM.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104573:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTHEW V. 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let your Light ſo ſhine before Men, that they may ſee your Good VVorks, and glorify your Father, which is in Heaven.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THESE words have a reference to the three foregoing Verſes, in which our Saviour applies himſelf to his Diſciples, and all ſorts of true Chriſtians; and requires them to ſet forth the Purity of their Doctrine, and the Purity and Exactneſs of their Lives to that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, that by the authority and ſoundneſs of their Doctrine and goodneſs of their Converſation, the Nation, or the World, might be kept from putrefying or ſtinking. And he compares the Chriſtian Church to a City ſet upon a high illuſtrious place, which is eaſily ſeen by all that travel near it; which City (if it be kept clean and beautiful) will attract and draw Travellers to it; but if otherwiſe, it will make them ſhun and abhor it. Wherefore our Saviour requires them all to ſet forth ſuch an eminent Light to the World both by their Doctrine and ſutable Life, that by their bright ſhining Luſtre the thick Miſts of Ignorance, and the groſſer Darkneſs of Sin and Wickedneſs might be diſpelled; and that others
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104573:5"/>ſeeing and beholding this Glorious State of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, might be invited thereby to glorify their Father which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Theſe words then of our Saviour, with reſpect to their Connexion with the former Verſes, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A Precept or Command to all ſorts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to preſerve pure and ſound Doctrine, and to lead exemplary Lives ſutable to their holy Faith and Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The words contain a powerful Argument to enforce good Chriſtian Practice, that others ſeeing your good Lives, may glorify your Heavenly Father; or, that the ignorant ſinful part of the World may receive ſaving Influences (by virtue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from the Purity of your Doctrine, and Goodneſs of your Lives) and ſo Glory may redound to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For the Precept or Command in general to all ſorts of Chriſtians to preſerve pure and ſound Doctrine, to ſee that their Copy be pure, and fair, and good (and this is of great import) for if our Faith, or any allowed Doctrines of our Chriſtian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety be ſtained or corrupted (eſpecially if ill Practice in any kind be the natural conſequence of ſuch allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctrines or matters of Faith) this tends to deſtroy the great end of all Religion, But (God be thanked) our Articles of Faith, and the allowed Doctrines of our Church, are ſound and good; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104573:5"/>is our Publick Worſhip of God corrupted ſo, that the publick Aſſemblies are become Schools of Idolatry and Wickedneſs, as perhaps may be with great truth ſaid concerning ſome other Church that exalts it ſelf, and looks big in the eye of the World.</p>
            <p>Here now (if time would permit me) I might take a very fair occaſion to repreſent the Faith, and Doctrine, and Government of our Church, which we all own our ſelves Members of; and to ſet forth the Purity and Soundneſs of it, and ſhew the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it to all that was owned by the Primitive Church in its beſt eſtate; to convince how full it is to all the purpoſes of a good Chriſtian Life; and to manifeſt plainly that neither our Holy Worſhip and Services are corrupted, nor doth the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> give any one Licenſe to Sin.</p>
            <p>But this is a large Field to enter into; and our Faith and Doctrine, and way of Worſhip and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, hath been ſufficiently ſet forth and juſtified by many Learned Men of our own Communion, and ſealed and confirmed by the Blood of Holy Martyrs.</p>
            <p>And therefore I ſhall ſay no more of the Copy; but I ſhall inſiſt upon that which our Faith and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and Diſcipline points at; which is to influence all Chriſtians ſo to live as our Faith and Doctrine and Government enjoins them to do, and thereby to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to the eye of the World the Excellency and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104573:6"/>Goodneſs of their Faith and Doctrine by their regular and holy Practices: For what will a good Copy ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy to them whoſe Lives do not write after it, and ſo adorn it? What doth it ſignify to talk of a good Way of Worſhip, if we do not frequent it, and join in it as devout Worſhippers too? What doth it ſignify to commend our holy Religion, which requires ſtrict Sobriety, Chaſtity and Modeſty of Life, and a due Fear and Veneration of God; and yet at the ſame time to lie wallowing in the Sins that are contrary to all this? What doth it ſignify to commend the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, and yet at the ſame time to deſpiſe and diſobey it?</p>
            <p>At the rate that moſt Chriſtians live, they do but blot and diſgrace their Copy, tho otherwiſe never ſo very beautiful and comely.</p>
            <p>Wherefore then to excite you all to manifeſt the Goodneſs of your Faith and Doctrine by your exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Lives:</p>
            <p>This I ſhall do in the following Method.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt,</hi> I ſhall urge thoſe Motives to Good Life, which our Common Chriſtianity affords us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2ly,</hi> And that with reſpect to this ſolemn Occaſion, I ſhall point out thoſe ſeveral Complaints that are made of ſome ſpecial Lets and Hinderances to an univerſal good Practice amongſt us; and I ſhall ſhew
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104573:6"/>what thoſe Lets and Hinderances are, and what muſt be the Cure and Remedy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3ly,</hi> I ſhall ſhew that to lead good Lives our ſelves, and to remove all thoſe Lets and Hinderances to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is the only way to bring Glory to god, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Reputation to our Holy Church, with Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Proſperity to this Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt,</hi> Then for the Motives to Good Life, which our Common Chriſtianity affords us; and to comprize them as ſhort as I can.</p>
            <p>You all know, when you were Baptized, what ſtrict Obligations that laid upon you to live well; and ſome of you know what farther additions you have voluntarily made by receiving Confirmation at the Biſhop's hands, and after that often receiving the Holy Communion. And who could now think that any perſon having paſſed under all theſe means of Grace, ſhould yet be only a Chriſtian in Title and Name? Let me perſuade all ſuch Chriſtians (if there be any ſuch here preſent) that they live according to their Chriſtian Profeſſion: For it is only ſo doing that can aſſure the ſincerity of their Faith; it is only ſo doing that muſt inſpirit and enliven their hopes of another and better Life; it is only ſo doing that can manifeſt their growth in Grace; it is only ſo doing that can aſſure their Victory compleat, and that the Seed of God abideth prevailingly in their Hearts: It is only a holy and regular Practice that can diſcover the effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of all our means of Grace, and that the end
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104573:7"/>of Chriſt's Death is anſwered by us; and this alone will convince Beholders that we are truly the Sons of God, and ſhall be Members of the Church Triumphant in the next Life, as we are living Members of Chriſt here: It is this alone that muſt diſpel all our Fears and Doubts when we come to die; and a good Chriſtian Practice will do it beyond the beſt Confeſſor in the World. And beſides all this, a ſincere good Chriſtian Life will help you to find Truth, and to keep cloſe to it when you have it; for indeed it is a love to Sin that makes men uncertain in a good Religion; and 'tis a godly Life that will prove the excellency of your Doctrine to others beyond all the beſt penn'd Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes in the World: for a good Life is an Argument to ſenſe, and convinceth the eye of the Beholder. Man cannot ſee the Heart; but we may read Men in their Lives: We know the Tree is alive by the Fruit. Indeed there are many external Acts of Worſhip and Duty, which a mere Hypocrite may perform with great applauſe; but when there is a thorow Change wrought in our Manners from all that is bad to all that is good, this is a viſible demonſtration that the Almighty Spirit of God hath been working in us, and that we are become the Children of God: When from an intemperate Life we are become ſtrictly ſober; when from malicious, haughty, and fierce and uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, we are come meek, and humble, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful; when from the love of the World we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come heavenly-minded; when from impatience under Croſſes and Troubles, we are become reſigned and ſubmiſſive to the Will of God in all things, and ſo from all Vices to the contrary Graces and Virtues; this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104573:7"/>is a viſible demonſtration of a mighty Change wrought in us by the Power of God: This is a plain diſcovery that the very Body of Sin grows weak, and is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by a Divine Omnipotent Power; and that the Grace of God is ſtrong and lively, and prevails over all our Corruptions.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Motives that might be enlarged upon to a Volume; but I can only point at thoſe Heads, which I doubt not but you can uſefully improve in your own private Thoughts and Meditations, which God grant you all may.</p>
            <p>I now proceed to the Second thing propoſed, which is to point out ſome ſpecial great Lets and Hinderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to an univerſal Reformation of Manners amongſt us: And theſe I ſhall ſet forth by way of Complaints, and they are ſuch as do require redreſs; and the firſt Complaint that I ſhall mention, is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Againſt the Guides of our Church; as if ſome of theſe Lights did not burn ſo clear in their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations as they ought to do. So far as this may be true, there ought to be ſpeedy Remedies applied: <hi>Nam quo magis quiſque eminet, eo gravius nocet malo exemplo, ſi ſe perverſe gerit. Vult ergo Chriſtus Apoſtolos eo majore ſtudio intentos eſſe ad piè ſancté<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vivendum quam quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet è vulgo obſcuros homines; quia omnium oculi in eos quaſi in lucernas conjecti ſunt; nec ullo modo ferendos eſſe, niſi vitae integritas doctrinae cujus ſunt miniſtri, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondeat.</hi> No doubt Miniſters ought rather to the more ſtrict than other Men, becauſe the conſequence
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104573:8"/>thereof is greater; for it the Shepherd wanders, no doubt but the Sheep will go aſtray. And beſides all this, <hi>Cum Paſtorum vita merito deſpicitur, eorum doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina &amp; verba conſequenter contemnentur.</hi> He that leads and idle Life may preach with Truth and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as did the Phariſees; but not as Chriſt, or as one having Authority.</p>
            <p>Thus ſpeaks the excellent Biſhop <hi>Taylor,</hi> in his <hi>Rules and Advices to the Clergy.</hi> But I come not here as an Informer againſt Men of the ſame ſacred Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter with my ſelf, and ſuch as, generally ſpeaking, are the greateſt Supporters of Religion in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: I ſay the greateſt Supporters of Religion in this Nation; for with reverence be it ſpoken to a higher Order, it is not a Triennial Light (tho ſhining never ſo clear) that will diſpel our Darkneſs; but it is theſe leſſer Lamps, always burning and ſhining in our Villages by holy Inſtructions and godly charitable Lives, that muſt diſpel our Fogs of Ignorance and practical Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Second Complaint</p>
            <p>Is of the want of conſtant catechizing of Children and Servants; or rather, I think, there is a great want of a uſeful and profitable way of inſtructing young people.</p>
            <p>It is certainly a great miſtake to think that merely the asking the Queſtions of the Church Catechiſm, and receiving the Anſwers, will ever make any great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104573:8"/>no nor reading an Expoſition upon ſome Article of Faith or other matters; This will not do; but it is applying our ſelves particularly to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular catechized Perſon by practical Queſtions, and receiving their Anſwers, confirmed by them by Proofs of Scripture, that muſt ſettle firm Grounds of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the Hearts of the Inſtructed. And what if Miniſters would beſtow one hour upon a Week-day upon this great Work, and at the ſame time caſt ſome Charity upon the poorer ſort, to encourage them to come conſtantly? I can aſſure from long experience, that they that do this, ſhould themſelves feel the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of it, and ſee the great benefit of their Care and Labours, to the Glory of God, and the good of many poor Chriſtians committed to their charge; and I do boldly ſay, there is no way like this to plant ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Goodneſs, and to undermine Schiſms and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to preſerve the Church both pure and in Unity and Peace. And beſides this good effect I have ſeen, it encourages the common People to bring up their children to reading; and by a ſort of emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation amongſt themſelves, it makes young Perſons to thirſt after and improve in divine practical Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg: It prepares them for Confirmation, and makes them fit to come early to the Holy Communion; yea, it cultivates their Manners betimes, and keeps them from the common Vices of the World.</p>
            <p>Third Complaint,</p>
            <p>And that is concerning the Male-adminiſtrations of ſome Officers in our Spiritual Courts, as that which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104573:9"/>greatly hinders a Reformation of Manners amongſt us. I do conceive it is of great moment to the true Intereſts of Religion, and the Service of the Church, that the chief Governours of thoſe Courts ſhould watchfully attend the management of buſineſs there, eſpecially in what concerns the exerciſe of Diſcipline againſt Offenders. I have made it my obſervation for many years, that wherever I have lived, ſome tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable care hath been taken for the cleanſing and repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Churches; but little or no care hath been taken about the living and walking Temples to ſcour off their Defilements. Betwixt the Churchwardens groſs negligence in diſcharging their Oaths by making due Preſentments, and the Remiſſneſs, or much worſe Practice of ſome inferiour Officers of thoſe Courts, there has been done little ſervice (ſo far as I could ſee) either to the reclaiming of any Offenders, or to the deterring any perſons from the too cuſtomary Sins of the World: Nor do I ſee how any great good can be expected, where Churchwardens ſeldom or never conſult their Miniſters about their Preſentments. Nor do the Spiritual Courts conſult with the Miniſters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the moſt proper way of dealing with lapſed Chriſtians; but matters relating to Offenders are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecretly hudled up (and it is to be feared ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times corruptly too) or if there be a publick Penance, there is ſuch a trifling management in the execution of it, as that it carries no weight, nor produceth any ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but turns all into a ridicule: but in ſpecial, as to Commutations of Penance, there hath been great ſwerving from the Rule. I am not ſo vain as to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and condemn in the general all private Penances,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104573:9"/>or Commutations of Penance, when they are done as the Canon directs, and thereby are made ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Intereſts of true Piety and Charity; but when they are made uſe of only to ſcrue the Purſe of the Offenders, and to ſatisfy the private greedy humor of ſome inferior Officers, who ſuck no ſmall advantage to themſelves by ſuch ſecret Sin-Offerings (as hath been done) you muſt give me leave to tell you, ſuch Practices become not Chriſtian Courts; but ſo far as this Charge amounts to, they are Scandals and Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and ought to be reformed.</p>
            <p>Theſe Spiritual Courts ought to ſtrengthen and aſſiſt the Miniſtry in their great Work, that ſuch as are too hard and rocky for our ſpiritual Weapons, may be broken and ſubdued by them to Repentance, or cut off and caſt out wholly, as rotten Members, by the ſacred and dreadful Cenſures of the Church.</p>
            <p>Fourth Complaint.</p>
            <p>The fourth great Complaint is againſt the main Body of Chriſtians, as if there were almoſt a total Eclipſe, a general failure in the Morals of Perſons in our Chriſtian Communion. The King and the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament do obſerve that Wickedneſs hath advanced amongſt us; and they do wiſely diſcern what Calamities and Miſchiefs a great Diſſolution of Manners will bring upon this Church and Nation; and therefore they are labouring by good Laws to ſtem the Tide, and to ſtop the great Inundations of Wickedneſs that threaten to everflow and drown us.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104573:10"/>And God knows our Danger is very great: for ſuch whoſe Eyes can reach but to a ſmall compaſs, cannot but ſee the Drunkenneſs, the Uncleanneſs, the Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Lying, the Killing, the Stealing, and what not, in ſome places or other of the Nation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needs muſt the Land mourn, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 4.2, 3. Yea ſo deeply radicated are ſome Sins, ſo ſtrengthen'd by Cuſtom, ſo emboldned by the Numbers offending, and ſo confirmed by Impunity, that could the Pulpit breath Fire upon ſuch as thoſe, it could not melt them into better manners. And beſides all this, that which I take to be the completion of this Nation's Miſery, is this, That Pariſh Officers, Conſtables and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens eſpecially, whoſe Oaths oblige them to bring Delinquents to juſt Puniſhhment; they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to complement away their Oaths, and their Souls too, for good Neighbourhood ſake: They can wipe their Mouths, and cry all is well, tho they cannot but ſee and know, if they were not wilfully blind, how by the wicked Lives of many under their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, God is provoked, Chriſtianity is wounded and ſcandalized; and by the ill Examples of moſt, the good diſpoſitions of others are corrupted, and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is propagated, to the great diſhonour of God, and reproach of our holy Religion. Wherefore, as this Occaſion invites me, I will give my friendly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Church-Officers; and I ſhall ſpeak my mind almoſt in the very words of that noble Divine Mr. <hi>George Herbert.</hi> In his Book of Advices to the Countrey Miniſters, amongſt many other good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, he counſels all Miniſters in their reſpective Cures to let their Churchwardens know, that the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104573:10"/>great care and charge of the Pariſh lies upon them; and indeed the whole Order and Diſcipline of the Pariſh is put into their hands. If the Miniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms any thing, it is out of the overflowing of his Conſcience, whereas the Churchwardens are to do it by Command and by Oath. By the Laws of the Kingdom the Churchwardens are to levy Penalties for negligence in reſorting to Church, or for diſorderly Carriage in time of Divine Service. And I may add, that by your preſent Articles of Enquiry, you are to preſent the groſs Immoralities of Offenders.</p>
            <p>But, as the ſame excellent Mr. <hi>Herbert</hi> goes on: It is the greateſt Honour of this World, ſays he, to do God and his Choſen ſervice, or, as <hi>David</hi> ſays, to be a Door-keeper in the Houſe of God.</p>
            <p>Now the Canons being the Church-wardens Rule, you are to read, or hear them read often, as alſo the Viſitation Articles, which are grounded upon the Canons; that ſo you may know your Duties, and keep your Oaths the better: in which regard, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the great conſequence of your Places, and more of your Oaths, you are by no means to ſpare any, tho never ſo great; but if, after gentle and neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Admonitions, they ſtill perſiſt in ill, you are to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them: for your Obligations to God, and your own Souls, are above any temporal Tie, any worldly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. Do well and right, and let the World ſink.</p>
            <p>And indeed, unleſs Pariſh-Officers will be watchful to diſcover Offenders, and then perform their Oaths,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104573:11"/>all hopes of a General Reformation of Manners muſt be at an end, and the Land muſt ſtill groan under the burden of Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Fifth Complaint</p>
            <p>Is concerning the great want of Family-Religion among the Generality of Chriſtians, and the not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying the Lords-day profitably in our Houſes, as well as in the Church.</p>
            <p>Next to the ſacred Miniſtry, there is nothing would conduce more to the reforming a corrupt World, and to the keeping up a due ſenſe of God and ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than the due care of Maſters and Miſtreſſes and Parents to diſcharge all that Duty which both Nature and Grace teacheth them; that is, to pray in and with their Families, and to inſtruct them; and to reſtrain and govern thoſe Children and Servants that are under their care and charge. And if thoſe Houſholders, whoſe daily neceſſities will not allow them much time for theſe Imployments upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther days of the week, would imploy the Lords-day carefully, both in the publick Aſſemblies and in their private Houſes, to benefit themſelves and thoſe that belong to their care, we might then hope to ſee Sin reſtrained, and Goodneſs univerſally planted: But until Families ſhall become Nurſeries of Religion and Good-manners, and ſhall become like little Churches and ſacred places both for good Inſtruction and holy Worſhip, no great Reformation is to be expected. Some may perhaps call this Puritaniſm; but call it
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104573:11"/>what they will, I take it to be an infallible truth, that it is exemplary Godlineſs that can only reſtore and preſerve the Church.</p>
            <p>Sixth Complaint</p>
            <p>Is of the Sacrilegious Inclinations of Perſons in our Communion: and that which unavoidably follows the making the Church poor, is the contempt of the Sacred Function. But this may ſeem to ſome a very remote Hinderance as to the reforming the World: but it is not ſo; for what great things can be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed where the Miniſters Maintenance is either wholly precarious, or if it be ſettled by Law, it is very ſtrait, poor, and neceſſitous? And a mean or precarious Livelihood too often cramps the Tongue of the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, and makes it afraid to ſpeak plain; and what is worſe, it hinders ſtudy, and begets ſervile and baſe Compliances: And in plain Engliſh, ſcandalous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings too often make ſcandalous Prieſts; and where it is ſo, what Reformation can there be hoped for?</p>
            <p>Our greateſt and beſt Men ſaw this Miſhief long ago, and that not only Churchmen, but ſome others of Great Name.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but mention one, a great Light, and Prelate of our Church, the famous Biſhop <hi>Jewel.</hi> In a Sermon of his before the then Queen, we have theſe words: <q>What may be gueſſed at their Intent who decay the Proviſions of the Houſe of God, and ſo baſely eſteem the Miniſters of the Goſpel, altho in other things they do well, altho they ſeem
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104573:12"/>to rejoice at the Proſperity of <hi>Sion,</hi> and to ſeek the ſafety of the Lord's Anointed? yet needs muſt it be that by theſe means foreign Power ſhall again be brought in upon us, ſuch things ſhall be done unto us as we before ſuffered in the times of Popery. And, ſaith the ſame Biſhop <hi>Jewel,</hi> the Parſonages and Vicarages are the very Caſtles and Towers of defence for the Lord's Temple; and if they be not better furniſhed with a due Maintenance, and made more ſecure againſt Contempt, we muſt expect God's Judgment upon us; and this noble Realm ſhall be ſubject to foreign Nations.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words to me are very remarkable, as falling from ſo great a Man; I wiſh they were not propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal: but yet when all is ſaid, 'tis not to be expected that the contempt of the Miniſtry ſhould wholly ceaſe. For the Sacred Order by their Office being bound to cry down the ways of Sin, which corrupt Nature cries up; the work of the Miniſtry being to promote Sobriety, Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, and to plant thoſe Graces in the Hearts and Lives of Men, which corrupt Nature and the Devil ſtrive againſt: This is ſo unthankful a work, to irritate and diſturb Mens Conſciences, as cloſe and ſound Preaching muſt needs do, to preſs againſt the bent of Mens ſtrong In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and to commend to them what they moſt hate; this is a work which will not procure to him much Honour and Eſteem that is imployed in it in this irreligious Age. And our Saviour hath told us long ago what we muſt expect from a wicked World, if we will be faithful in our places: <hi>The World cannot
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104573:12"/>hate you, but me it hateth, becauſe I teſtify of it that the Works thereof are evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs it may ſeem very ſtrange to a thinking Man, that in a civilized Nation a Man of God ſhould be deſpiſed; a Man of God by his ſacred Character and Meſſage, and whoſe Office it is to guide and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct Souls to Heaven. Little do Chriſtians conſider how much they owe to the main body of the deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Clergy.</p>
            <p>By them you are baptized, by them you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in all ſaving Knowledg; by their Prayers your Souls do receive aid and aſſiſtance from Heaven; by their Prayers Judgments are kept off from a People; at their hands you often receive the Bread of Life, and by them your departing Souls are commended to God; and if there were any Magiſtrates here, I would tell them, and juſtify it too, that the Peace and Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Kingdom is more owing to the Pulpit and an orthodox regular Clergy, than to all the Courts of Judicature. 'Tis not the Magiſtrates Sword alone that would preſerve you, if the daily and weekly Labours of the Miniſtry did not inſtil good Principles, and keep the Conſciences of men awake, and make men more afraid of Sin than all your Axes and Rods can do: It is the Miniſters Labours that diſpel that Ignorance, ſo far as it is diſpelled amongſt us: It is the Miniſters faithful Labours that break the force of mens Corruptions, and make them more dutiful to God, and ſubmiſſive to their Governours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104573:13"/>And therefore if the Parſonages and Vicarages be the very Caſtles and Towers of defence for the Lord's Temple, and the greateſt ſecurity for the State too, ſure then it highly concerns all Orders of Men to aſſiſt and protect them, and to contribute all they can to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them from contempt, and to ſtrengthen them in their great work of promoting Religion, and depreſſing Vice and all manner of Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>I have now done with the great Lets and Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derances of an univerſal Reformation of Manners, and it is no difficult thing to point out what muſt be the Cure.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A devout, faithful and laborious Miniſtry, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with a due Maintenance, and made more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure againſt contempt.</item>
               <item>2. The Officers of Pariſhes muſt be ſuch as fear God, and that underſtand the weight of an Oath, and the great conſequences of diſcharging it.</item>
               <item>3. Family Religion muſt be kept up.</item>
               <item>4. Children and Servants muſt be well inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</item>
               <item>5. The Spiritual Courts muſt give their utmoſt aſſiſtance to the Miniſtry.</item>
               <item>6. A Religious Magiſtracy muſt give their helping hand to puniſh Vice, and encourage Goodneſs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:104573:13"/>And when all theſe ſhall mutually conſpire to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the great ends of Religion, we may then hope for a new face of things; we may then hope for a new Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſneſs; we ſhall then behold the Kingdom of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour exalted amongſt us, which is the hearty deſire of all Good Men.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to my third an laſt point, which is to ſhew, That to lead good Lives our ſelves, and to remove all thoſe Lets and Hinderances which keep others from doing the ſame, is the only way to bring Glory to God, Honour and Reputation to our Holy Church, and true Happineſs and Safety to our Church and Nation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, to promote univerſal Goodneſs by our living well, and diſcouraging Vice, brings Glory to God, as it doth ſenſibly and experimentally commend the ways of God to a poor ignorant brutiſh World: It lets the World ſee that the ways of Religion are ways of Pleaſantneſs, and all her Paths are Peace. A good Chriſtian Life, as it gives inward joy to the Practiſer, ſo it ſweetly inſinuates a good liking into the Beholders; it ſtrangely attracts the Affections of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and by a ſecret inviſible force it charms the Paſſions, and delights the Beholders. The glorious Attire of Chriſtian Graces, ſuch as Meekneſs, Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Modeſty of Mind; fervent Piety to God, and as fervent Charity to Man; undiſguiſed Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; Sincerity in all our Dealings; evenneſs and equality of Mind in all conditions and eſtates of our
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104573:14"/>Life; Conqueſt over Paſſions; Contempt of the World; and Sollicitouſneſs for nothing, but to keep up and maintain a joyful Entercourſe betwixt God and our Souls: Such a Divine Temper as this doth ſtrangely affect and attract, and muſt inſinuate a good reliſh into all Beholders; and it is my firm be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief that were Perſons that are of a good Communion but more exact in their Lives to the Reformed Copy that is before them, it would mightily ſupercede the neceſſity of much writing to juſtify and recommend our way of Worſhip: for were Mens inward Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions more ſubdued by the force of that Religion which they profeſs, we ſhould find little to do but to love God, and love one another; and the ſweet Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh which ever attends a conſcientious well-ſpent Life, would ſo confirm and ſettle good Chriſtians in their way, that they would never doubt or ſtagger, and many other Beholders that are unſteddy and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, would be more eaſily drawn to join with that Communion of Chriſtians where they ſee a Divine Preſence and Force (and ſo much Comfort as a good Life produceth) than by all other Arguments in the World.</p>
            <p>And this leads to a ſecond Conſideration, to enforce good Chriſtian Practice in our ſelves, and to diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage Vice in others.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For it ſhews our Principles to be ſound and good, and that we firmly aſſent to them as ſuch: It convinceth the World that our Doctrine and way of Worſhip is from God: This Men will be apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104573:14"/>when they ſee the powerful and viſible Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it in the change of mens Manners from bad to good: This ſatisfies men beyond all other Arguments, that there is a Divine Preſence amongſt us, and that there is a ſpecial Aſſiſtance and Bleſſing concurring with the means of Grace that we make uſe of; and it doth moſt plainly evince that God's Grace is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon us in vain. I would to God that this moſt excellent Argument (for ſo the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans accounted it) were not ſo much loſt as it is, as to its due force upon Beholders, by the bad Examples of too many Chriſtian Profeſſors. Thoſe firſt and beſt Chriſtians could boaſt of the Truth, the Goodneſs and Excellency of their Religion, and Soundneſs of their Doctrine, from the admirable Efficacy and Power it had upon the Hearts and Lives of thoſe that recieved it. All this is plain from ſome memorable Paſſages in <hi>Lactantius</hi>'s <hi>3d</hi> Book <hi>de falſa Sapientia;</hi> and alſo in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places of <hi>Origen,</hi> too long here to be recited.</p>
            <p>But <hi>3ly,</hi> It brings Glory to God, and great Good to others, as it demonſtrates our Religion to be a practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable thing, and that the hardeſt Duties may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Arguments alone will hardly invite the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of People to ſerious and ſtrict Religion, where good Examples are wanting; yea Examples will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade more effectually than all the beſt framed Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the World: for men love to ſee whether the Ways be paſſable or no, before they adventure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; eſpecially where Fleſh and Blood tells them there are ſome Difficulties to encounter, ſome Rocks and Uneaſineſſes to climb over; and that they may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104573:15"/>happen to meet with much ill uſage too in their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to Heaven, even from ſuch as pretend to be Friends and Fellow-Travellers. But when men ſhall ſee by the Courage and Victory and good Examples of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that commend theſe ways of Religion, that the worſt of Difficulties may be overcome, and are ſo, by the ſame Fleſh and Blood with themſelves; this animates and enlivens their Spirits, and takes off all Objections ariſing in their Minds from the difficulty of the Attempt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A good Life, and diſcouraging of Vice, brings Glory to God, as it declares to the World that we ſtedfaſtly believe, that without a regular Piety and ſtrict Obedience to the Laws of Chriſt, none ſhall be ſaved. This will viſibly diſcover to the World what our Belief is, and what our Opinions are: This will manifeſt that we entertain no corrupt and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Principles; and we our ſelves might appeal to this as a Teſt, if our Lives were but regularly pious and uniformly good: for a Hereſy, or dangerous Error in the Judgment, will for the moſt part appear in the Practice of him that owns it. And let me tell you, it will not be eaſy to convince any one that our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in matters of Religion are ſound, if our Morals are bad; and of this I am ſure, that few will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced that we believe a good Life to be abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation, if we do not lead good Lives our ſelves, and ſhew alſo, by our zeal, our diſlike of Wickedneſs in others.</p>
            <p n="5">5. and laſtly, A thorow Reformation of Manners
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104573:15"/>brings Glory to God, as it gives the Almighty a free occaſion to manifeſt himſelf in that great Attribute he moſt delights in, which is in ſhewing mercy to a ſinful Nation, and diſpoſing all things for the Happineſs and Safety of it. God will never look favourably upon us, until our crying Sins be removed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we do believe that there is a Divine governing Providence, which bleſſeth or chaſtiſeth a Nation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they either fear or diſhonour him, we muſt then believe that all our private and publick Happineſs and Safety will depend upon our holy living, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenancing Vice. Your very Safety and Proſperity in any kind reſts move upon this Baſis than upon all our wiſeſt Counſels, or the force of Arms: and the very Safety and Reputation of our Church, both at home and abroad, depends upon a thorow Reformation of Manners: yea the Peace, and Honour, and Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of your Families depends upon it; and what is much more valuable, I am ſure your inward Peace and comfortable hopes of another Life reſts upon your regular good Chriſtian Practice. In a word, your Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm requires it, and the care of your Childrens Souls and others of your Family exacts this Duty of you, to live well your ſelves, and to diſcourage Sin in others. And for many of you that hear me, I muſt plainly tell you, that your very Offices and ſolemn Oaths do bind you to proſecute the wicked Doers; and to all of you I ſay, your Allegiance to God and the King exacts all this at your hands.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let the ſum of our Thoughts bend this way; let this be the chief end of all our Study, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104573:16"/>and Reading: Let this be the end of all our Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Praying, and counſelling, and reproving, and correcting, to ſave our own Souls, and the Souls of others. Then will the Almighty ſhine upon us, and give us his Bleſſing; and all <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall behold and ſee that we are not only mighty in Battel, but mighty in Prayer too, and ſhall be forced to confeſs that God is with us, and on our ſide, becauſe by due fearing and ſerving him we are become a wiſe and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding People.</p>
            <p>But to conclude:</p>
            <p>Since ſo auguſt and puiſſant a Prince leads the way; ſince a Prince mighty in Battel to defend and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect us, is neither afraid nor aſhamed to engage him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reſolutely under the deſpiſed Banner of the Croſs, and to fight Chriſt's Battels againſt the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a wicked World, and commands us all not only to live well, but to attend and aſſiſt him in our ſeveral Offices and Places to diſcourage and ſuppreſs the Corruptions of the Age we live in; I do take it to be a ſpecial and ſignal Call from Heaven to you all to join unanimouſly in this great work of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to amend a corrupt World. And if any Magiſtrates or inferior Officers ſhall neglect to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute his Majeſty's pious Intentions, they will have a great deal to anſwer for, not only to the King, but to the Great God the King of Kings; and they will bring the Guilt of others Sins upon themſelves and the whole Nation: For the Connivance of Governours makes the Sins of private Perſons the Sins of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity; and altho the Puniſhment of private perſons
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104573:16"/>or particular men may be deferred to a future State, yet Communities as ſuch (as one well expreſſeth it) having no Reſurrection in the World to come, they may juſtly expect the fruits of their Delinquencies in this preſent Life.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it cannot be hoped or expected that ſo great a work as the Reforming a polluted Age can be brought to any great effect, unleſs all that have the leaſt ſtamp of Authority upon them, ſhall put their helping hand to this great Work; unleſs Parents and Maſters of Families ſhall begin at home; unleſs Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Magiſtrates, and all inferior Pariſh-Officers ſhall conſpire and conjoin in this glorious Work: Let us therefore pray to Almighty God that he would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire the Hearts of all Orders and Eſtates of Men in this our holy Church, that every Member of the ſame, in his Place and Office, Spiritual or Civil, may gird themſelves with a true Chriſtian Zeal and Courage to countenance Goodneſs, and to bring all Wickedneſs into a juſt ſhame and contempt; that ſo God may be glorified, and many Souls ſaved, and that God may delight to dwell amongſt us, and that we may all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice and be glad in the Peace and Proſperity of our Church and State.</p>
            <p>DEO GLORIA.</p>
            <p>Now the God of Peace, that brought again from the Dead our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that great Shepherd of the Sheep, through the Blood of the everlaſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good Work to do his Will, work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104573:17"/>in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be Glory for ever and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Grant, we beſeech thee, Almighty God, that the Words we have heard this day with our outward Ears, may through thy Grace be ſo grafted inwardly in our Hearts, that they may bring forth in us the fruit of Good Living, to the Honour and Praiſe of thy Name, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Peace of God, which paſſeth all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, keep your Hearts and Minds in the Knowledg and Love of God, and of his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord: And the Bleſſing of God Almighty, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, be amongst you, and remain with you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
